PROJECT TITLE :FISHING ROUTE OPTIMIZER
 🐠 Indian Fishing Navigator:


A comprehensive and culturally aware fishing route optimization platform built specifically for Indian fishing communities. The application leverages traditional knowledge, monsoon forecasting, and AI-based navigation to ensure safety, efficiency, and sustainability.


 🚨 Problem Statement:

Indian fishing communities face significant challenges due to unpredictable weather patterns, lack of access to real-time navigation tools, and limited digital support tailored to regional needs. Existing navigation apps do not consider cultural fishing practices, traditional boat types, or monsoon-specific hazards.


 📌 Project Description:

**Indian Fishing Navigator** empowers coastal fishermen across India by combining AI-powered route optimization with region-specific data. It supports traditional fishing practices, provides emergency alerts, and integrates localized languages and government regulations. Designed to operate under both digital and low-connectivity conditions, it is a vital companion for safer and more sustainable fishing.


🚀 Features:

 🌊 Indian Coastal Waters Support
- Coverage: Arabian Sea, Bay of Bengal, Indian Ocean
- Monsoon-aware weather forecasting
- Mapping of traditional fishing grounds
- State-specific fishing laws and regulations

 🐟 Indian Fish Species Recognition
- Identification of Pomfret, Kingfish, Mackerel, etc.
- Seasonal catch prediction
- Regional fishing pattern analysis
- Traditional knowledge integration

 🗺 Regional Customization
- Language Support: Hindi, English (framework for regional languages)
- Emergency Contacts: Indian Coast Guard (1554), VHF Channel 16, Fisheries Helpline (1962)
- Cultural adaptation of UI/UX
- State fisheries department integration

📱 Smart Features
- AI-powered route optimization for Indian waters
- Fuel-efficient route guidance
- Real-time weather & sea condition updates
- Cyclone & monsoon alert system
- Emergency call simulation (with offline fallback)
 🌍 Indian Coastal Regions Covered

- West Coast**: Gujarat, Maharashtra, Goa, Karnataka, Kerala  
- East Coast**: Tamil Nadu, Andhra Pradesh, Odisha, West Bengal  
- Islands**: Andaman & Nicobar, Lakshadweep  


 🧭 Cultural Considerations

- Respect for traditional fishing calendars
- Support for non-motorized and traditional boats
- Community-based route and catch sharing
- Offline-first design philosophy for low-signal areas


 🌤 Weather Integration

- Monsoon predictions (Southwest & Northeast)
- Cyclone warnings and alerts
- Integration with IMD and traditional forecasting methods
- Wave height, wind speed, temperature, and humidity tracking



## 🛠 Tech Stack Used

| Category             | Technology                  |
|----------------------|-----------------------------|
| Frontend             | Flutter (Dart)              |
| Backend (optional)   | Firebase / Node.js (planned)|
| Weather API          | IMD API / OpenWeatherMap    |
| Geolocation & Maps   | Google Maps SDK / Leaflet   |
| Language Support     | i18n Flutter Package        |
| Alerts               | Firebase Cloud Messaging    |

---

 📦 Installation & Setup

Installation & Setup Instructions

🛠 Prerequisites

Flutter SDK (with Dart) → Install Guide

VS Code or Android Studio

Android emulator or physical device

Internet connection (for weather & maps)


Run this to verify setup:

flutter doctor


---

📁 Project Setup

1. Download or clone the project
If using Git:

git clone https://github.com/EZHIL1108/MatysaN-Tech-titans/blob/main/aml%20daniel.zip


2. Install dependencies

flutter pub get


3. Run the app

flutter run




---

🧪 Optional

Web version:

flutter config --enable-web
flutter run -d chrome

Build APK:

flutter build apk --release

Ensure Flutter SDK is installed and your environment is set up with either a connected device or an emulator.

 
 👥 Team MemberS:

     DANIEL AROCKIARAJ.B
     DHANYASRI.V
     DEVIPRIYA.R
     EZHIL.P
     
             



